Your Highness
殿下、
Be careful in all matters
どうかお気をつけて。
Don't worry
安心しろよ
Stop swaying
行ったり来たりするでない、
It's distracting
目障りじゃ。
Or perhaps, Your Excellency
いっそ
Could pay someone to perform a ritual
金を投じて術師を請い、
To make Yu Gong appear from the Imperial City Guard
虞宮を皇城司から引きずり出してしまっては いかがでござろうか？
Enough, both of you
言を控えよ
Your Highness
殿下
Tell us
その日の状況を
About that day
お聞かせくだされ
Yu Gong, Chancellor of the Imperial Academy
国子監祭酒・虞宮は
Was like a teacher to me
我にとって半ばの師とも言うべき者
That day
この詩にて
He introduced his disciples to me
彼は己が門弟を我に引き合わせ
After several rounds of wine
酒を飲み過ぎし後
Your Highness
殿下
He got carried away
興が乗って
Composed a sentimental poem
一編の憂苦の詩を詠んだのじゃ
Never forget
「神州奪還」とする志
The resolve to recover our divine land
決して忘るることなかれ！
Now
されど今
His poem
その詩は
Has been framed by my elder brother and the Chen family
兄上と陳家の手により
As inciting rebellion
「謀反煽動」の罪に陥れられ
This is a disaster
大禍となりつつある
What exactly did Yu Gong say?
では、虞宮はいったい何を言いしや？
What he wrote doesn't matter
詩の内容自体はさほど重要ではない
Since
殿下も場に
Your Highness was present that day
在られしゆえ
Prince of Ning and the Chen family
寧王と陳家は
Must be trying to drag Your Highness into this
必ずこの件を殿下に絡めようと画策したのだ
The urgent matter
急務は
Is to eliminate all those
あの日の酒楼（しゅろう）に
Who were present at the tavern that day
居合わせし者を一掃し
To cut ties with Yu Gong
虞宮と距離を置き
And ensure this matter
此の件が殿下に
Does not touch you at all
微塵たりとも及ばぬよう万全を期すことにある
Minister Xie speaks so casually
謝尚書
How many must die?
その一言で何人を殺すやもしれぬぞ。
Your Highness
殿下
Yu Gong has great prestige
虞宮は国子監や
In the Imperial Academy
民間においても
And among the people
非常に高い名声を持ち
He has also recommended many talents to Your Highness
殿下のために多くの才を推薦してくれた方ゆえ
If Your Highness abandons him
殿下が彼を見捨てれば
What will scholars think?
天下の学徒は如何に思う？
Moreover
まして
If you don't protect your own
自らの側近をも保てぬとなれば
In the future
以後
Which court official
朝の文武は
Would dare serve Your Highness
誰が命を賭して
With wholehearted loyalty?
殿下に尽くさんや？
A benevolent ruler cannot stand in troubled times
仁君は乱世に立たず
Your Highness aims to recover the northern lost lands
殿下が北地奪還を志すなら
If you hesitate for one subordinate
一人の食客のために躊躇い
And create a rift with His Majesty
陛下との間に隔たり生じば
Then
それは
That would be a greater loss
真に得る所少なし
Of course
もとより
How to decide
決断は
Is up to Your Highness
殿下の御心次第に候。